SHAOJIE JIANG

Senior Machine Learning Scientist

Homepage: https://shaojiejiang.github.io/

Email: shaojie.jiang1@gmail.com

I worked as a Senior Machine Learning Scientist at Huawei R&D Center Amsterdam. I worked on training Huawei's ChatGPT models, and am responsible for the Reinforcement Learning algorithm development and model training. More broadly, my work involves chatbots, information retrieval and conversational QA systems. In parallel, I am completing my PhD at the University of Amsterdam. I have interned at Replika.ai and Amazon.com.

WORKING EXPERIENCE

2022.07 - 2023.08

Huawei R&D Center, Amsterdam, the Netherlands Senior Machine Learning Scientist Area: ChatGPT, Chatbots and Conversational QA Systems Responsibility:

- Reward model and PPO algorithm development and model training (core of the ChatGPT model)
- Designer and main contributor of Chair, a research toolkit in Python (70% of commits), which is capable of training SFT, RM, and PPO models through one line of command
- Lead of ChatEval challenge project at DSTC 11
- Contact person of the Conversational AI project
- Contact person of DReaMS Lab work package 3

Skills: Python, PyTorch, NLP, NLU, LLM, Chatbot, Information Retrieval, Retrieval-Augmented Generation, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Model Architecture Design, Reinforcement Learning (RLHF), Research, Problem Solving, Model Training/Finetuning, Model Evaluation (Human Evaluation), Data Science, Data Engineering, Leadership, Project Management, Teamwork, Architecture (XGPT toolkit), CI/CD, Docker, SaaS, MaaS, AWS, Linux, Git, Jupyter

2021.02 - 2021.07

Replika, San Francisco, USA

NLP Research Intern

Project: Improving Generative Dialogue Engagingness

Team: AI Research Team **Mentor:** Artem Rodichev

Outcome: A chatbot model with improved engagingness, and a follow-up research paper accepted at CHIIR 2023 (see below)

Skills: Python, PyTorch, NLP, LLM, Chatbot, Deep Learning, Research, Problem Solving, Model Training/Finetuning, Model Evaluation (Human Evaluation), A/B Testing, Data Science, Data Engineering, Teamwork, Docker, SaaS, MaaS, GCP, Linux, Git, Jupyter

2020.07 - 2020.09

Amazon.com, Inc., Amsterdam, The Netherlands

Applied Science Intern on NLP

Project: Customer Review Summarisation

Team: Subjective NLP **Mentor:** Alex Klementiev

Outcome: An automatic aspect extraction system for customer

reviews

Skills: Python, PyTorch, NLP, NLU, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Research, Problem Solving, Model Training/Finetuning, Data Science, Data Engineering, Teamwork, Docker, SaaS, MaaS, AWS, Linux, Git, Jupyter, SageMaker

EDUCATION

2017 - present

University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands

PhD Candidate

Research area: Open-domain Dialogue Systems

Supervisors: Prof. dr. Maarten de Rijke & Dr. Svitlana Vakulenko

Thesis plan: Expected to finish by October 2023

2014 - 2017

Northwest A&F University, Yangling, China

Master of Engineering

Thesis: Research on Feature Representation and Optimization Methods

in Structured Object Tracking Supervisor: Prof. Jifeng Ning

2010 - 2014

Northwest A&F University, Yangling, China

Bachelor of Engineering

Thesis: Implementation of Single Image Haze Removal Using Dark

Channel Prior

Advisors: Dr. Yaojun Geng and Prof. Jifeng Ning

PUBLICATIONS

Shaojie Jiang, Ruqing Zhang, Svitlana Vakulenko, and Maarten de Rijke. "A Simple Contrastive Learning Objective for Alleviating Neural Text Degeneration." Submitting to the TOIS journal (impact factor 4.657).

Shaojie Jiang, Svitlana Vakulenko, and Maarten de Rijke. "Weakly Supervised Turn-level Engagingness Evaluator for Dialogues." To appear in CHIIR 2023 as a full paper. Source code link below (Lit-Seq).

Shaojie Jiang, Ruqing Zhang, Svitlana Vakulenko, and Maarten de Rijke. "A Simple Contrastive Learning Objective for Alleviating Neural Text Degeneration." arXiv preprint arXiv:2205.02517. 2022. Source code link below (Lit-Seq).

Shaojie Jiang, Thomas Wolf, Christof Monz, and Maarten de Rijke. "TLDR: Token Loss Dynamic Reweighting for Reducing Repetitive Utterance Generation." arXiv preprint arXiv:2003.11963. 2020. Source code link below (TLDR).

Shaojie Jiang, Pengjie Ren, Christof Monz, and Maarten de Rijke. "*Improving Neural Response Diversity with Frequency-Aware Cross-Entropy Loss.*" In The World Wide Web Conference, pp. 2879-2885. ACM, 2019. Source code link below (FACE).

Shaojie Jiang, and Maarten de Rijke. "Why are Sequence-to-Sequence Models So Dull? Understanding the Low-Diversity Problem of Chatbots." In Proceedings of the 2018 EMNLP Workshop SCAI: The 2nd International Workshop on Search-Oriented Conversational AI, pp. 81-86. 2018.

Shaojie Jiang, Jifeng Ning, Cheng Cai, and Yunsong Li. "Robust Struck tracker via color Haar-like feature and selective updating." Signal, Image and Video Processing 11, no. 6 (2017): 1073-1080.

Jifeng Ning, Jimei Yang, **Shaojie Jiang**, Lei Zhang, and Ming-Hsuan Yang. "Object tracking via dual linear structured SVM and explicit feature map." In Proceedings of the IEEE conference on computer vision and pattern recognition, pp. 4266-4274. 2016.

OPEN SOURCE CONTRIBUTIONS

XGPT Toolkit https://github.com/ShaojieJiang/xgpt

Lit-Seq project https://github.com/ShaojieJiang/lit-seq

TLDR project https://github.com/ShaojieJiang/tldr

FACE project https://github.com/ShaojieJiang/FACE

AWARDS

2019 Invited by NLP Summit at Google Zurich

2018 Student Travel Grant for the 2nd SCAI Workshop

2017	Faculty Outstanding Master Thesis Award
2013	National Endeavor Scholarship

National Endeavor Scholarship

TEACHING AND SUPERVISION

2021.02 - 2020.03	Teaching Assistant for Master AI course Information Retrieval 1
2019.11 - 2020.06	Master AI Thesis Supervision: Traian Vidraşcu, "Link Prediction for Software Graphs using Inbound and Outbound Neighborhoods"
2019.11 - 2020.06	Master AI Thesis Supervision: Kai Liang, "Neural Hierarchical Text Classification with Transfer Learning Approaches"
2019.04 - 2019.07	Master Data Science Thesis Supervision: Savvina Daniil, "Training Support Vector Machines Using Multi-Party Computation"
2019.06 - 2019.06	Teaching Assistant for Master AI Project-AI course on "Repetition Reduction for Chatbots"
2018.10 - 2018.12	Teaching Assistant for Master AI course Information Retrieval 2 on "Hierarchical Neural Response Generation"
2018.01 - 2018.06	Master AI Thesis Supervision: Ricardo Fabián Guevara Meléndez, "Task-Oriented Dialog Agents Using Memory-Networks and Ensemble Learning"

COMMUNITY SERVICE

2022 Reviewer of TOIS

2021 Reviewer for JSCT and TALLIP

2020.02-2021.02 Member of PhD Council at the Informatics Institute of the Univer-

sity of Amsterdam

2020 Reviewer for TOIS, ACL, EMNLP and EACL

2019.09-2020.11 Representative of Informatics Institute on PhD Council of the

Faculty of Science of the University of Amsterdam

2019.03-2019.06 Subreviewer for SIGIR and CIKM

MORE SKILLS Unity, LaTeX, Rust, Photography

REFERENCES

Prof. dr. Maarten de Rijke My PhD Supervisor, Distinguished University Professor AI & IR at University of Amsterdam, Director Innovation Center for Artificial Intelligence. Email: m.deRijke@uva.nl

Dr. Jun Luo Former Colleague, Machine Translation team lead at Huawei R&D Center Amsterdam. Email: junluo@huawei.com

October 6, 2023